Baddar Naeem Minneapolis, MN 55403 5712650817 baddarnaeem2@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY:**

7+ years of experience in Software Testing with designing Test Plans, defining Test Cases, developing and maintaining Test Scripts, analyzing Bugs and interacting with development team members in fixing the defects and agile testing.

Substantially experienced in writing and executing Test Cases and Test Scripts, mentoring Client staff, working with overall team to meet project goals.

Experienced to work closely with Developers to refine tests and identify, document and assist in resolution of defects before software is released.

Experienced to identify Test Objectives and using them to design and develop manual and automated Test Cases as appropriate to validate Positive and Negative conditions.

Experienced of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), Agile, RUP, Technical writing and Documentation.

Extensively experienced in Functional, Regression, Smoke, Black box, and User Acceptance (UAT) testing.

Expertise in Automated-testing includes concentrated application, training and interaction with HP Tools like ALM/ Quality Center.

Good at defect-reporting and defect-tracking using HP ALM/ Quality center.

Knowledge in writing SQL queries and executing procedures to perform back end testing for the expected results.

Extensively experienced in maintaining test scripts with QTP/UFT.

Experienced in creating, enhancing and maintaining high-end Test scripts for various functional and regression testing using QTP/UFT and VBScript.

Good Knowledge of using QTP/UFT for Regression testing.

Extensively experienced in using VB script to develop Automation Frameworks.

Experienced in writing VB script for creating Descriptive programming, Function library, Optional steps, Capturing values using QTP/UFT.

Good team player with active participation in meetings with the testing, development teams and Clients.

Energetic and good communication, leadership and problem solving skills.

Troubles shoot Production issues and helped Customer Solution team to resolve it; Good analytical skills.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS:**

LANGUAGES / SCRIPTING: SQL, C, C++, Java/J2EE, Perl, Visual Basic, VB Script, JavaScript, XML, HTML, DHTML, C#, CSS

DATABASE: SQL Server, Oracle, DB2, MS Access, MSP Reflections Sessions

SERVERS: Apache, Tomcat, Web Logic Server

TESTING/PERFORMANCE TOOLS: HP UFT, HP QTP, HP ALM, HP Quality Center

BUG TRACKING TOOLS: HP ALM, HP Quality Center

**OPERATING SYSTEMS**: Microsoft Windows, Linux/UNIX

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:**

**Wells Fargo** 

Saint Louis Park, MN

QA Automation Tester Level 4/Project Manager (with BA, manual testing experience in Agile Scrum)

May 2017 - Present

### Responsibilities:

Worked as a Scrum Master in Agile Scrum Environment.

Led teams in Waterfall and Agile Environments.

Worked as a mid-level project manager for one project.

Worked with client's Business, technical and user stakeholders to define issues, and designed enhancements in a Business Analyst function.

Working on multiple applications at the same time.

Worked solely in waterfall automation teams and can handle all responsibilities solely.

Conditioning of loans in MSP and other applications.

Designed test suite for Automated Tests with UFT.

Worked as a BA to gather all the requirements and create test cases in Agile Scrum Environment.

Worked as a Manual Functional Tester and created manual test cases out of the requirements using BRDs and FSDs.

Done ALM synchronization of test cases.

Sub-Lead role in all applications.

Team work with teams in India, North Carolina, San Francisco and Iowa.

Done Back-end testing and validations.

Executed test cases from Jenkins.

Used MSP Reflections Sessions to condition testing loans in test environments.

Generated UFT Scripts with Standard, Text, Table Checkpoints and also Synchronization Points.

Conducted automation functionality and regression testing for each build and version using UFT.

Involved in developing scripts using descriptive programming in UFT.

Created Custom functions, Dictionary objects, Data driven automation framework using VB Scripts.

Participated in test case automation using a structured, Keyword Driven Framework with UFT.

Involved in executing and maintaining UFT Automation frameworks.

Conducted data-driven testing using parameterization in UFT.

Designed, developed and executed the Test Plans and Test Cases in ALM.

Developed an integrated Test Plan covering the main functions of the design parts of the application.

Involved in gathering requirements from the business analysts and creating Test plans.

Attended daily scrum calls as part of agile methodology.

Performed Smoke, Integration, Functional, Regression, System, Acceptance and Usability testing during different stages of the application development.

Participated in use-case reviews, authored, and reviewed test planning artifacts in HP ALM.

Provided an aggregated, cross-application project view of quality status and defect trends and managed and enforced consistent workflows and processes using HP ALM.

Used HP ALM to attach screenshots, and associated the defect with the proper severity and priority, and linked the related Test Script, from which the Defects were generated.

Found critical bugs in the application, weekly Reporting through Bug Reports and Maintenance Traceability Matrix using HP ALM.

Tested on Different databases like Oracle, SQL server using SQL Queries.

Run sanity tests in support of production release testing.

Performed web service testing using SoapUI.

Ensured the execution of UAT test cases and documentation of test results.

Planed and delivered demonstrations of new functionality to business users.

Implemented onsite-offshore Global Delivery Model for this project.

Provided status reports to appropriate groups concerning test issues and progress.

Performed tasks independently with little supervisor.

**Environment**: HP ALM, HP UFT, MS Excel, MS Office, .NET, MS Visio, Java, J2EE, Java Script, VBScript, AJAX, DB2, Oracle, HTML, SQL, XML, Windows, Jenkins, MSP Reflections Sessions, Selenium

Verizon Ashburn, VA QA Automation Engineer Sept 2015 – Apr 2017

## Responsibilities:

Worked with client's Business, technical and user stakeholders to define issues, and designed enhancements in a Business Analyst function.

Designed a test suite for Automated Tests with UFT.

Generated UFT Scripts with Standard, Text, Table Checkpoints and also Synchronization Points.

Conducted automation functionality and regression testing for each build and version using UFT.

Involved in developing scripts using descriptive programming in UFT.

Created Custom functions, Dictionary objects, Data driven automation framework using VB Scripts.

Participated in test case automation using a structured, Keyword Driven Framework with UFT.

Involved in executing and maintaining UFT Automation frameworks.

Conducted data-driven testing using parameterization in UFT.

Designed, developed and executed the Test Plans and Test Cases.

Developed an integrated Test Plan covering the main functions of the design parts of the application.

Involved in gathering requirements from the business analyst and creating Test plans.

Attended daily scrum calls as part of agile methodology.

Performed Smoke, Integration, Functional, Regression, System, Acceptance and Usability testing during different stages of the application development.

Participated in use-case reviews, authored, and reviewed test planning artifacts in HP ALM.

Provided an aggregated, cross-application project view of quality status and defect trends and managed and enforced consistent workflows and processes using HP ALM.

Used HP ALM to attach screenshots, and associated the defect with the proper severity and priority, and linked the related Test Script, from which the Defects were generated.

Found critical bugs in the application, weekly Reporting through Bug Reports and Maintenance Traceability Matrix using HP ALM.

Tested on Different databases like Oracle, SQL server using SQL Queries.

Run sanity tests in support of production release testing.

Performed web service testing using SoapUI.

Ensured the execution of UAT test cases and documentation of test results.

Planed and delivered demonstrations of new functionality to business users.

Implemented onsite-offshore Global Delivery Model for this project.

Provided status reports to appropriate groups concerning test issues and progress.

Performed tasks independently with little supervisor.

**Environment**: HP ALM, HP UFT, MS Excel, MS Office, .NET, MS Visio, Java, J2EE, Java Script, VBScript, AJAX, DB2, Oracle, HTML, SQL, XML, Windows.

Bank of America Wilmington, DE QA Engineer Mar 2013 – Aug 2015

## Responsibilities:

Created usage scenarios and executed them in order to test a product from a user perspective.

Created Test scenarios for claim selection, generated claims and data validations.

Developed comprehensive Test plans based on system requirements.

Involved in Requirement reviews and Design Review.

Involved in testing of the online web application.

Documented all test results, identified and summarized discrepancies.

Performed various types of process evaluations during each phase of the software development life cycle, including review, walk through and system testing.

Developed the Test Cases to test Functionality and Interface of the application using HP Quality Center.

Used HP Quality Center to manage the requirements and Test cases.

Performed Manual testing using MS-Excel and HP Quality Center.

Used HP Quality Center to log defects and generated defect reports and graphs.

Involved in Backend testing by writing SQL Queries.

Involved in Functional, System and Regression Testing using QTP.

Developed VB scripts in Quick Test Pro to perform end to end testing.

Used Data sheets in Quick Test Pro to import data from data tables for conducting the Data Driven Testing.

Involved in Web Service Integration testing using Quick Test Pro.

Developed User Defined Functions Library with reusable VBScript functions using QTP.

Performed Test case execution using a keyword Driven Framework with Quick Test Pro.

Supported in creating test cases to check the functionality of the enhanced application and performed User Acceptance Testing (UAT).

Worked in executing and analyzing various queries and creating reports.

Provided UAT testing status information to the quality assurance lead, project manager, and various business stakeholders.

Developed timelines for project delivery and managed project.

**Environment**: MS Visio, MS Excel, MS Office, Java, J2EE, SQL Server, HP Quality Center, HP QTP, Windows, UNIX, Oracle, MS Office, CSS, C++, C#.

UnitedHealth Group Baltimore, MD Software Tester Nov 2010 – Feb 2013

## Responsibilities:

Analyzed the business requirements and involved in the review discussions.

Drafted Test Cases based on Functional Specifications and System Specifications.

Prepared of Test Plan and analyzed integration system impacts.

Involved in Manual Testing of the application for Negative and Positive scenarios.

Developed smoke test scripts in traditional automation approach.

Used Quality Center to analyze, track and report defects.

Worked on uploading all the Test Cases to the Quality Center for the current and prior releases.

Worked in Backend Testing using SQL Queries.

Used SQL queries to ensure integrity and consistency of the data.

Trained and mentored new team members in automation tool QTP.

Developed Test Scripts for Data Driven tests using QTP.

Inserted Text checkpoints where needed, to compare the current behavior of the application being tested to its behavior in the earlier version using Quick Test Pro (QTP).

Performed Team management and other day-to-day activities.

Performed automation execution and analysis and prepared daily summary reports.

**Environment**: J2EE, Java Script, MS Office, MS Excel, MS Visio, C++, C#, VB Script, Oracle, Quality Center, QTP, Java, Windows, UNIX.

#### **EDUCATION:**

# Ghulam Ishaq Khan Institute of Engineering Sciences and Technology, Pakistan

**Bachelor of Engineering** 

### **University of California Irvine**

Applied Project Management Project Planning Project Initiation Project Execution Project Closing